All right, we got good news, Americans.
We got away with our illegal occupation
of Syria. Good for us. No consequences.
We are invincible.
Who else should we invade since that
went so well? Well, uh, just a reminder,
the US has been illegally occupying
Syria since 2014. But now that regime
change has softened things up for us,
we're suddenly on friendlier terms.
Washington wants to make that official.
The New Arab reports that a senior US
delegation is set to arrive in Damascus
in the coming days to sign an agreement
with the Syrian government to formalize
the US presence, the military presence,
marking a significant shift in US
policy. So, this would be retroactive,
meaning we'll just pretend it was cool
that we were there all along, even
though it was not. This is a textooked
pivot being framed as a step towards
legitimacy but really a way to cement US
influence in Syria. Ensuring that the e
that we have easy access to strategic
territory, trade routes, oil. Remember
President Trump during his first term
saying we just wanted to keep them from
having the oil, keep it for ourselves.
So yeah, we got away with it. All good.
All good. No accountability, no
reckoning, not even a slap on the wrist
for the chaos, the displacement, the
suffering that the United States has
enacted on Syria since uh well, if we're
really going to it's not just the Obama
years. We got to rewind the clock all
the way to the 1949 CIA backed coup. If
you like us are lifelong learners, then
this is a great place to go to school
without really going to school. You
don't have to get up early like your
kids and pack a lunch. You can take
courses that interest you to further
your own education based on what you're
interested in. Now, this is self-guided
and they have more than 40 free online
courses such as the works of CS Lewis,
the stories in the book of Genesis, the
meaning of the US Constitution, which is
constantly uh debated in this country,
the rise and fall of the Roman Republic.
So, we want to recommend that you sign
up. Here's a good one. Introduction to
Aristotle's ethics, how to lead a good
life. Uh so again, these are self-paced
and you can start whenever and wherever.
So start your free course today. Head on
over to hillsdale.edu/redacted
to enroll. There's no cost and it's easy
to get started. One more time, that's
hillsdale.edu/redacted.
Former CIA agent and whistleblower John
Kuryaku joins us to discuss because he
has been talking about this for a long
time. So um up top, all good. Yeah. Way
to go, John. We got away with it. Yeah.
Does this feel good? Should we take a
victory lap? Who else should we invade?
Winning. I know, right? We're going to
have We're going to have 2,000 troops
freed up. We can now invade pretty much
anybody we want. Uh, I will say a couple
of things have surprised me about this.
Uh, first of all, have you seen it
anywhere in the American media? Cuz I
haven't, and I look for it. It was the
Turks who leaked this story 5 days ago
with no following statement uh from the
Pentagon. So the Turks are the ones that
are saying, "Hey, you know, the
Americans are engaged in uh discussions
with the new Syrian government. Those
discussions are taking place in Ankura.
And what it looks like is going to
happen is that the US is going to
withdraw except for one small base which
we may keep just one person on. One
person just to say that there is a US
presence in Syria which is nuts to me.
But the bottom line is what what you
just said. Right. That's what I'm going
to say. Sign me up for that job. Oh, no
problems protecting yourself when you're
the only American in an isolated base in
southeastern Syria. So, when you have
been murdering civilians from that base
for a decade, you are exactly right.
You're exactly right. I I was having a
conversation with a friend earlier today
about the illegality of um sending
combat troops overseas without approval
from Congress. And you know, when you
think about it, this is an impeachable
offense that has been committed by every
single president since Harry Truman.
Every single president. The last time
the US Congress declared war was on
December the 8th, 1941, the day after
the bombing of Pearl Harbor. But the
Constitution is very clear. If we are
going to engage in war, it has to be
after a vote uh in Congress. and we just
don't bother. You know, Congress has
attempted half measures over the years.
Um, you know, they'll they'll do
authorizations for use of force. Those
are just resolutions. They don't have
the the impact of law. Um, they they
just pretend that the president is is
not sending troops or they talk about
approving uh on a on a budgetary basis,
an appropriations basis, enough to feed
and clothe and arm the troops. But
that's not the same as a declaration of
war. So now we're going to withdraw
these combat troops uh from Syria. They
should never have been there in the
first place. But are we bringing them
home? Remember, this hasn't been
reported by the US government. It's the
Turks telling us what the Americans are
doing. Are we going to send them to
Somalia or to the Sahel where we already
have other combat troops or are they
actually coming home? We don't know.
Well, what we've been seeing is that
Israel is starting to step up attacks on
Syria. So maybe we want to get the heck
out of there. Is there an angle there
and sort of let them have at it? There
very well could be. The conventional
wisdom was that the Israelis and the
Turks were the big winners in the fall
of Bashar al-Assad. Everybody agreed
that that was the case. They were the
big winners. And you remember in the in
the immediate couple of days after
Assad's overthrow, the Israelis went in,
they pushed in past Golan um just a
couple of miles. And everybody said,
"Oh, well, you know, they should they
shouldn't have done that, but we
understand that the Israelis probably
want to have a little bit of a buffer
zone." Well, listen, there's nothing in
international law that says you can have
a buffer zone. Number one. Number two,
the Israelis never said that they were
going to stop there and have a buffer
zone. Since then, and it's been a couple
of months now, they have repeatedly
bombed Syrian territory, including
inside the city of Damascus,
and it looks like that's going to be the
Israeli policy now, that nothing is
going to change with the Israelis as far
as military attacks on Syria. So, it
could be, and forgive me if this sounds
a little bit conspiratorial, but it
could be that the US doesn't see an
upside to being in the middle between
the Israelis and the new Syrian
government. So, it's better just to
leave.
You know, Matt Gates, Congressman Matt
Gates was on the floor of of Congress
before he left Congress pushing to get
us out of Syria. He was he was sort of
vilified by all those neocons in
Washington who wanted to continue this
war. We were we were giving him huge
rounds of applause. We're an anti-war
show. Uh and we can't stand neocons. And
so pushing to get them out of of Syria,
bring our troops home. Um he was
vilified for it. Of course that didn't
pass. But the argument they used, John,
as you know, was that it it it would
undermine the United States of America.
It would make the United States of
America less secure. That's what they
told us. If we brought these forces
home, you saw it all over social media,
Matt Gates. No, no, this will make us
less secure here in the United States.
How is that possible? Right. It it just
it's an incredible
faulty analysis to me. First of all, if
you want to occupy a country like Syria,
and I don't know why you would want to
occupy a country like Syria, you're
going to need four maybe 500,000 troops,
not 2,000 troops. The reason why we sent
uh 2,000 troops during the Obama
administration was very was very simply
to counter the Russian presence. We
didn't have any reason to be in Syria
other than to stick our thumb in the eye
of the the Russians. Now, the Russians,
of course, had been invited into Syria
by the Syrian government. Well, now the
Russians are gone, and there's no reason
to be in Syria anymore. And so, I think
that's the calculation that has been
made. It this had nothing to do with
with violence. It had nothing to do with
war. It had nothing to do with
terrorism. ISIS is gone from Syria. It's
been gone for a long time. This had to
do with saving face,
right? Steven Gowen's great book called
Washington's long war on Syria goes back
to Bashar al-Assad's father and how the
United States hated him because he was
an Arab nationalist meaning he thought
that Arabs should build things for
themselves. They should because Syria
doesn't have a ton of oil. They have oil
but not a ton considering when you
compare it to their neighbors. But they
thought that Arab money should be used
for Arab prosperity and we could not
have that. And that's why we've always
set our sights on imploding Syria. And
what do you think of that? I think that
is exactly right. You know, we we danced
with with um Hafz al-Assad, Bashar
al-Assad's father a couple of times, and
things were especially good during the
uh the Gulf War in 1990 911 because the
George HW Bush administration convinced
the Syrians to to send a couple of
hundred troops to uh to uh Kuwait to
help liberate the country. So, it was
all good. But you're right, Arab
nationalism has always frightened the
United States and it's always frightened
the Gulf Arabs because they're
royalists. They're they're all run by
royal families. And so this idea that a
country like Syria could maybe join with
a country like Egypt, which they did.
They changed the name briefly to the
United Arab Republic. uh it was a they
they merged as as one country that just
panicked the west because they were
non-aligned and in Washington if you're
non-aligned that used to mean ah you're
really secretly with the Soviets and it
panicked the Saudis and the Kuwaitis the
Bahrainis at all because they were
anti-royalist
well now here we are all these years
later and the Saudis are finally willing
to establish diplomatic relations with
Syria. Why? Because the Assads are gone
and there is a former leader of ISIS and
al-Qaeda now running the country. That
if we tick off the scariest ones, right,
there was Gaddafi, there was Saddam
Hussein, and there were the Assads. We
got them. Those were people who wanted
prosperity for their own nations, and we
thwarted that. So Clinton, as Hillary
Clinton said, we came, we saw, we killed
Gaddafi. Yeah. So the neocons are
high-fiving themselves over this, and
the rest of us can just feel absolutely
horrid in our stomach for what we did to
those civilians. That's how I feel about
it. I want to puke. John, what I got to
ask you. We had Syrian journalist,
friend of the show, Kavor Almasian, on
the show, you know, many, many times.
But but Kavor told us in the after the
fall of Assad and the you know the
takeover by Golani and and all of this
and this basically CIA backed coup that
led to this whole thing. Um I said you
know do you think Syria will exist any
longer? And he said I I'm sad to say I
don't think Syria will exist anymore.
You know the Turks to the north, you
have Israel. Do you think what does the
future of Syria look like to you? I
think Syria will uh continue to ex
exist, but perhaps not looking exactly
the way it has always looked. Uh the
Turks are there to stay. They're going
to be there forever. They talk about a
buffer zone. They talk about wanting to
work with the the Syrian Kurds. They
can't work with the Syrian Kurds. They
don't they don't they're not able to
work with any Kurds. Turkish Kurds,
Iraqi Kurds, Iranian Kurds, Syrian
Kurds. Makes makes no difference. the
the Turks hate the Kurds, so they're
going to keep this buffer zone. Uh the
Israelis apparently intend to remain uh
as occupiers even if it's not a lot of
territory. The Israelis are not going to
leave Syria. And there still are areas
of Syria where there are armed uh bands
of uh Muslim fundamentalists.
And so, you know, God forbid that the
that the Iraqis decide they need a
buffer zone, for example, then what do
we do? And then Lebanon is falling
apart. What does it mean for the border
between Lebanon and Syria? So, I think
Syria will continue to exist, but maybe
not exactly the way it looks today.
Our guest is John Kiryaku, someone who
knows this area better than just about
anyone. Always appreciate your insights,
John, for keeping it real. My pleasure.
We have a comment right now that says,
"Who cares about Syria?" I mean,
okay, we we kill people there, John. Why
should we care about Syria? Yeah,
because Syria is a key to stability in
the greater Middle East. You know, it's
it's bad for everybody when governments
are not viable. You mentioned Syria's
oil. They have just a little bit of oil,
enough for themselves, not really enough
to export. But it's in America's
interest for the Syrians to have a self-
sustaining economy, for example, because
when people are able to make a living,
they don't turn to religion uh as a as
an opiate. They don't uh they're they're
not easily radicalized. They don't seek
to to leave the country and go overseas
where they could be radicalized. We need
for the Syrians to to be able to build
an economy that keeps Syrians in Syria
and everybody happy.
Right. Thank you. Right. And when you
had Assad there able to control these
more fundamentalist sects and be able to
keep, you know, so that you didn't have
that spilling over. Um Yeah. I mean
then, you know, you saw over the past 24
actually the past six hours, John, we
see head of al-Qaeda calling for the
assassination of President Trump. That's
right. Um I mean, you know, before we
get you out of here, your comments on
that, saying that we need to these, I
guess, Muslim radicals need to rise up
and now assassinate President Trump.
This is coming from the head of
al-Qaeda.
That was a very alarming report when it
uh when it first came out. But you have
to look at what al-Qaeda is right now.
The al-Qaeda that he represents is is
the core al-Qaeda. It has I'm going to
go out on a limb and say a few dozen
core members. They have no access to
President Trump. I think the bigger
threat to US interests is al-Qaeda in
the Sahel in Africa places like
Moretania, Mali, Nijir, Bkina Faso, uh
even parts of Ghana and Nigeria. It's
it's exceedingly dangerous there now and
a lot of those governments are in danger
of falling. That could draw the United
States in. It's not a direct threat to
President Trump. Um, but in terms of a
threat to President Trump, I think
really that's all talk.
Someone in the chat says, "Why is that,
Clayton? Because we effed around over
there for the last hundred years. Cut
the [__] We don't belong there."
Hallelujah. Yeah. They sell us lies.
Like they always Yeah. They sell us lies
through Sirius. So, we need to
constantly have this exercise. And we
see you. We don't believe this [__]
That's We don't We don't believe it.
That's right. Yeah. All right. Thank you
for this, John Keryaku. Always a
pleasure to have you. Thanks, John. Good
to see you both.